<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble address of the right honourablehe [sic] Lords spiritual &amp; temporal in Parliament assembled, presented to His Majesty the seventh day of March, 1694 An His Majesties gracious answer thereunto.</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1695-03-07</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2801C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232052</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900087</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900087</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170892</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170892)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2515:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble address of the right honourablehe [sic] Lords spiritual &amp; temporal in Parliament assembled, presented to His Majesty the seventh day of March, 1694 An His Majesties gracious answer thereunto.</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1695-03-07</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Lords.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Charles Bill and the executrix of Thomas Newcomb, deceas'd, printers to the Kings most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694 [i.e. 1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dates are given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1694-1702 : William III) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170892:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Humble ADDRESS Of the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual &amp; Temporal In Parliament Aſſembled, Preſented to HIS MAJESTY The Seventh Day of <hi>March,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>AND His Majeſties GRACIOUS ANSWER THEREUNTO.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill</hi> and the Executrix of <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> deceas'd, Printers to the Kings moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty. 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:170892:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Veneris 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Martij, 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in Parliament Aſſembled, That the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of this Houſe, Preſented to His Majeſty Yeſterday at <hi>Kenſington,</hi> and His Majeſties moſt Gracious Anſwer thereunto, ſhall be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed: And that the Lord Keeper of the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> do Appoint the ſame accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Matth. Johnſon,</hi> Cler' Parliamentor'</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Parliamentary_address">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170892:2"/>
            <head>The Humble ADDRESS Of the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal In PARLIAMENT Aſſembled.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Sabbathi 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Martij, 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, having Reſolved by the Unanimous Vote of this Houſe, That the Send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a Fleet into the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing it in thoſe Parts, has been to the Honour and Advantage of Your Majeſty and Your Kingdoms; and having Spent ſome Time upon Conſideration of the Condition of the Fleet both at Home and Abroad, and of the great Encreaſe of the Naval Force and Strength of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Conceive it to be our Duty to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the Kingdom, Humbly to Repreſent, That the Honour and Safety of this Nation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Providence of God, chiefly Depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Your Strength at Sea. And whereas, by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170892:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>long Continuance of this War, the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Your Ships muſt have been Diminiſhed, and thoſe Remaining greatly Impaired, We think it of the higheſt Importance to Your Majeſties Service, and the Security and Intereſt of Your People, That You would be Pleaſed to Give ſuch Speedy and Effectual Directions for the Repair and Encreaſe of Your Royal Navy, as may Enable Your Majeſty, not only to Continue a Strength in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> during this War, which may be Superiour to that of our Enemies, but likewiſe to Maintain ſuch a Force here at Home, and in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> as ſhall be a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for our Coaſts and Plantations, and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of our Trade, and Sufficient both for the Annoying of our Enemies, and for the Protecting and Convoying all ſuch Stores and Proviſions as muſt be Sent to the Fleet in thoſe Parts; upon the Effectual and Timely Providing whereof, the Safety of that Part of Your Majeſties Navy does ſo much Depend.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="response_to_Parliamentary_address">
            <p>To which His Majeſty was pleaſed to Return a moſt Gracious Anſwer, to the Effect following:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>I</hi> Am very Senſible how much Our Safety depends upon Our Strength at Sea, and therefore cannot but Deſire the Encreaſe of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And I ſhall not be Wanting to do what is in My Power, as to the Matters mentioned in your Addreſs.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
